<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and perfect discourse of three great accidents that chaunced in Italie within twentie and sixe dayes Worthie to be published, the better to know the Lords workes, and to teach vs, that with all humilitie wee should accept of whatsoeuer his will and pleasure is.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105570</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841297</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841297</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5871</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04146)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5871)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 571:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and perfect discourse of three great accidents that chaunced in Italie within twentie and sixe dayes Worthie to be published, the better to know the Lords workes, and to teach vs, that with all humilitie wee should accept of whatsoeuer his will and pleasure is.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>13, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Wolfe dwelling in Distaffe Lane neare the signe of the Castle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On leaf A1 recto is a woodcut of a ship.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Italy --  History --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:5871:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:5871:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of ship</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5871:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:5871:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
            <p>A TRVE AND perfect diſcourſe of three great <hi>accidents that chaunced in Italie</hi> within twentie and ſixe dayes.</p>
            <p>WORTHIE TO BE <hi>publiſhed, the better to know the</hi> Lords workes, and to teach vs, that with all humilitie wee ſhould accept of whatſoeuer his will and pleaſure is.</p>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe</hi> dwelling in Diſtaffe Lane neare the ſigne of the Caſtle. 1588.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5871:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:5871:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
            <head>A TRVE AND PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect diſcourſe of three great <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents that chaunced in Italy, within</hi> twentie &amp; ſix dayes, worthie to be publiſhed, the better to know the Lords workes, and to teach vs, that with all humilitie wee ſhould accept of whatſoeuer his will and pleaſure is.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are come letters written to certaine Marchants of credite in this towne being ſtrangers, ſome dated the twentieth of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember laſt, other ſome the ſecond of Ianuarie, and other on the ſixt of the ſame moneth, wherein are ſet downe the ſeuerall accidents hereafter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the which are worthie to be reade and noted of euerie good Chriſtian, to the end, that with loue one towards an other, and godly feare towards the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God, wee ſeeke in all dutifull manner to ſerue him, who ſuffereth not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5871:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->ſuch plagues, but by his eſpeciall ſecret iudgement for the puniſhment of the vngodly and example of his choſen people.</p>
            <p>On the thirtenth of December, <hi>1587.</hi> and according to our courſe o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> writing on the third of the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth, being Sunday, about two of the clocke in the after noone, the aire being verie thicke and darkiſh with often lightenings and thunder, that di<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beate vpon one of the tower of th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> caſtle of <hi>S. Elmo</hi> in the citie of <hi>Napels,</hi> wherein there was thrée thouſant barrels of gunne pouder, the which being by this meanes ſet on fire, made ſuch a terrible noiſe, that it ſéemed the whole went topſie turuey, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw in like ſort all the houſes that were within the ſame caſtell: Of the which houſes there remained not any ſtone one vpon another, ſo that, if in ſome part of the caſtle the walles had not remained and ſome rampiers, there woulde haue beene no remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of any Caſtle or Tower that ſhould haue béene there. And there
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5871:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->eſcaped not aboue tenne perſons that were within the ſaide caſtell, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie there are two hundred bodies deade, being men, women and children: it hath alſo ſpoiled many other, as it is thought, houſes and churches to the number of one thouſand, and hath not left ſo much as the verie ſtones that were paued in their places, there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt not one houſe in this poore citie, as it now may be termed, but hath felt in ſome ſorte, part of this puniſhment: and in concluſion, he that hath not ſéene this miſerable act, will hardly belieue it, nor the miſerable hurt that was there done. But that, that is more miraculous and worthie to be noted, is that the wife of the Captaine of the ſaide caſtell, two dayes before this chaunced, ſaide often times to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, that ſhe woulde not tarrie in the caſtell, her huſband aſking her, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſhe aunſweared that for thrée ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall times one after an other, ſhe dreamed, that ſhe ſhould with the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell be blowen vp into the ayre, of the which her ſpéeches, her huſbande for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5871:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->twiſe or thriſe made b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t a Ieſt, but in the end, his wife was ſo importunate, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eight dayes before, he was content to houſe himſelfe, with al his whole houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in the city, ſomewhat far off from the caſtell: &amp; by this meanes they auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the danger which otherwiſe might haue fallen vpon them, beings as it ſhould ſéeme by the ſpeciall fauor of God. And the common opinion of all men is, that if the ſaid tower had ſtoode towarde the citie, as it was towarde the ſea, it had ſpoiled the moſt parte of the citie. God the author of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes bleſſe and defend both them and vs from ſuch like extremities, and giue vs grace ſo to leade our liues, that we may be readie whenſoeuer it ſhal pleaſe him to call vs.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Genoa</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond of Ianuary, 1588. the which is according to our order the xxiii. of December before, they doo write as followeth: Here is arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from <hi>Spaine</hi> a ſhip called <hi>Piuma,</hi> the which had taken in, in the Ile of <hi>Maiorica</hi> thrée men that had been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before by the Turkes and made
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5871:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->ſlaues, the which men told ſhem of the loſſe of thrée Gallies, in order as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signior Giannettino Spinola</hi> in the Ile of <hi>Euiſa,</hi> with the Gallies of the prince <hi>D'Oria,</hi> that came out of <hi>Spain,</hi> beeing now aduertiſed, how that there were ſeuen ſmal Gallies of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Pirates in the Ile of <hi>Spalmado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> from thence ſeuen or eight miles off, he was deſirous to go and fight with them, and preſently hee furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed eight Gallies with his beſt and readieſt men to fight, as well of Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and Marriners, as others: and thus they ſet themſelues forwarde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſaide Ile of <hi>Spalmadore,</hi> but for that the wind was both great, and alſo contrarie vnto them, the one of the ſaide Gallies could not paſſe the point of the ſaide Ile, and ſo hee tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned backe againe, the other ſeuen with great force went forward, and founde the ſeuen Turkiſh Pirates and their Gallies, who looked for nothing leſſe than this, notwithſtanding they tooke courage vnto them, and foure of thoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5871:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->Turkiſh Gallies gaue themſelues to fight, and the other thrée fled. The foure ſmall Gallies of the Turkes hauing ioyned themſelues with thrée Gallies of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and fighting on both ſides moſt valiantly, there aroſe ſuch a great tempeſt, that theſe Gallies beeing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled togither were driuen vpon a Rocke, and ſo ſpoiled their Gallies, and many of their men were drowned, the other who ſaued themſelues being come on land, they fell to fighting afreſh.</p>
            <p>And the other thrée Gallies that were fled, winding about the Iland, found faire weather, and imagining what chaunced, they landed two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred foureſcore and ten men, the which they ſent to finde the other that were a fighting: they adioyning themſelues with their other fellowes Turkes fiue the moſt part of the Spaniardes, and got againe many other Turkes that were ſlaues to the Spaniards: and it is thought that the Turkes car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away a great quantitie of money, but of this there is no certaintie. The
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5871:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->one of the thrée Gallies was of <hi>Cigala,</hi> the other of <hi>Centurione,</hi> and the third of <hi>Grillo,</hi> all marchants of <hi>Genoa,</hi> who were fraught by Spaniards, the which thing is not to them alone a great hinderance, but alſo to ſuch others as were intereſſed in the mony.</p>
            <p>He that wrote, wrote to the Lords of <hi>Genoa</hi> in this order. It is not long ſince I wrote vnto your <hi>Exellencies,</hi> how that in this town there haue béene diſcouered thinges neuer heeretofore heard off. That is, of a ſect or ſchoole of witches, and that many of them being examined of the fact, confeſſed. Now I write againe vnto you, ſignifying that after that the Vicars of the Reuerend <hi>Signior Albengo,</hi> and the Inquiſition haue taken this matter in hand, there remained about eightéene or twentie condemned, the greater part of them haue confeſſed voluntarily, &amp; without any torment at all, beſides which there remaineth as yet foure ſuſpected, who haue not yet confeſſed any thing, and beſides, there is in priſon a witch, who hath confeſſed very much. So that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5871:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->the aforeſaide Vicars procéede in their buſines maruellous well, not reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting rich nor poore, and this day as vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other daies they ſit in counſell for the ſame purpoſe. The common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this place doo ſhew themſelues in ſuch ſort deſtrous of the cutting off of theſe witches, that they haue taken vp money at intereſt to helpe the ſaid Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars. Tomorrow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Vicars depart hence, to go to <hi>Albenga</hi> there to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſult, with the Reuerend <hi>Signior</hi> of <hi>Alben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga,</hi> and ſo they meane preſently to turn againe hither to make an end.</p>
            <p>And truely (right honourable Lords) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dealings of theſe euil perſons are moſt ſtraunge, in ſo much that they can cauſe tempeſts with thunder and lightnings and ſuch other like euil, all the which ſeeme them, as they make ſhew, to bee of account, for that they preſume to be able to doe farre greater things: and that is more, they kill their owne children and kinſmen: and euen as it were in a triſe, they will leape vpon the backe of the diuel, who ſhall be in the likenes of a Ram: and goe to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5871:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->their congregation for to conclude vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the doing of much euil, euen in the preſence of the diuel, who ſitteth there as chiefe iudge in likeneſſe of a king, before whom they doe openly deny God, and bequeath them ſelues to the diuel. Theſe ought to be warnings vnto euerie good Chriſtian to be ready, and prepared againſt the deceiptful en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements of the diuel, the continuall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie of mankind, and who (as ſaith <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in his Goſpel) was a murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer euen from the beginning, and as <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaith in his epiſtle, he goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout like a roaring Lyon, ſéeking to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and therefore we haue great néed earneſtly to pray vnto almightie God, that he will aſſiſt vs with his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and ſo to guide vs, that we be the better able to reſiſt the vile temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Sathan, and folowing his holy ſteps, his name may be in vs glorified, and we in the end made partakers of his heauenly bleſſing, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
